Guide to the Arthur Gold and Robert Fizdale Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Arthur Gold and Robert Fizdale papers
1954-1991
GEN MSS 1012
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.88
(5 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
The collection consists chiefly of correspondence to the piano duo Arthur Gold and Robert Fizdale. Correspondence, dating from the mid 1950s to the end of their professional career in the early-mid 1980s, includes large files for Fizdale's family and their mutual friend Harold Talbott, as well as small files for writers, artists and performers, cultural figures and philanthropists, and others. Correspondents include: Brooke Astor, Mikhail Baryshnikov, Elizabeth Bishop, Eleanor Clark, Alice Esty, Sir John Gielgud, Peggy Guggenheim, Fairfield Porter, Jeremy Robbins, and Dorothea Tanning. Other papers include manuscript material, photographs, printed ephemera, and material relating to the couple's book on Sarah Bernhardt.
Gold, Arthur
Fizdale, Robert, 1920-1995
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Serendipity Books on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arthur Gold (1917-1990) and Robert Fizdale (1920-1995)
Arthur Gold and Robert Fizdale met while studying with Rosina Lhévinne and Ernest Hutcheson respectively at Juilliard. In 1944 the pianists formed a duo that survived until their retirement in 1982. They made their debut at the New School for Social Research in 1944 in a recital of music by John Cage and their reputations in the standard repertory were established with a Town Hall recital in 1946. Gold and Fizdale revived the Mendelssohn 2-piano concertos and expanded the repertory by commissioning works from Milhaud, Poulenc, Rieti, Berio, and other composers. Arthur Gold was born 6 Febuary 1917 in Toronto and died 3 January 1990 in New York City. Robert Fizdale was born 12 April 1920 in Chicago and died 6 December 1995 in New York City.
Biographical information taken from Harvard Biographical Dictionary of Music (1996): 271, 319.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists chiefly of correspondence to the piano duo Arthur Gold and Robert Fizdale. Correspondence, dating from the mid 1950s to the early-mid 1980s, roughly the end of their professional career, includes large files for Fizdale's family and their mutual friend Harold Talbott, as well as small files for writers, artists and performers, cultural figures and philanthropists, and others. Correspondents include: Brooke Astor, Mikhail Baryshnikov, Elizabeth Bishop, Eleanor Clark, Alice Esty, Sir John Gielgud, Peggy Guggenheim, Robert F. Kennedy, Fairfield Porter, Jerome Robbins, and Dorothea Tanning. Other papers include manuscript material, photographs, printed ephemera, and material relating to the duo's book on Sarah Bernhardt.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1954-1984. Series II. Other Papers, 1970-1991.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Pianists -- United States -- Archives; Photographic prints; LGBTQ resource; Astor, Brooke; Baryshnikov, Mikhail, 1948-; Bernhardt, Sarah, 1844-1923; Bishop, Elizabeth, 1911-1979; Clark, Eleanor, 1913-1996; Esty, Alice, 1904-2000; Gielgud, John, 1904-2000; Gold, Arthur; Guggenheim, Peggy, 1898-1979; Fizdale, Robert, 1920-1995; Porter, Fairfield, 1907-1975; Robbins, Jerome, 1918-1998; Talbott, Harold; Tanning, Dorothea, 1910-2012
- Correspondence, 1954-1984; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. correspondence contains large files of correspondence for Fizdale's family and their mutual friend Harold Talbott, as well as small files for writers, artists and performers, cultural figures and philanthropists, and others. Correspondents include: Brooke Astor, Mikhail Baryshnikov, Elizabeth Bishop, Eleanor Clark, Alice Esty, Sir John Gielgud, Peggy Guggenheim, Robert F. Kennedy, Fairfield Porter, Jerome Robbins, and Dorothea Tanning.
  - Angleton, Carmen, 1963-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Astor, Brooke, n.y. February 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Auden, W. H. (Wystan Hugh), 1962 February 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Azzam, Issam, 1970-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Baryshnikov, Mikhail, 1980 January 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Begley, Auka; Begley, Louis, 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes film negatives
  - Bellas, Kay Mazzo, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Berman, Eugene, 1954-1969, undated1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bernac, Pierre, 1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bernier, Olivier, 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bishop, Elizabeth, 1969-1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Blaine, Nell, [1962?]-1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Blake, Chris, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Includes clipping
  - Boleyn, Eleanor, 1981 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Borreau, Annette, 1978-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Bouchonnet, N. D., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes photograph
  - Boxer, Arabella, 1972 October 9 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brante, S. [Marina?] de, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Includes photographs
  - Brunhoff, Marie-Claude de, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bruno, Michelle, 1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Burckhardt, Rudy, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cahen-Salvador, Gilbert; Cahen-Salvador, Jean, 1980 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Campbell, Virginia, 1958-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Carmichael, Bessie, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Chambers, Lucille, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Chapon, François, 1980 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Chatwin, Bruce, 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Clark, Eleanor, 1980 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Cowles, Chandler, 1972 November 20 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Craft, Robert, 1980, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Croisset, Ethel de, 1980, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Dernis, Colette, 1981 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Di Modrone, Verde Visconti, 1983 April (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Doll, Eugenia, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Douglas, Jean; Douglas, Gordon, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Drogheda, Joan, 1980 August 28 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - d'Erlanger, Margaret, 1970 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Esty, Alice, 1965 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Faure, Genevieve, 1980 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Fizdale family, 1954-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 41-46)
  - Gielgud, John, 1983 January 21 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Givenchy, Hubert de, 1980 February 12 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Gnoli, Annie, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Grant, Margaret, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Gregory, Alexis, 1963-1984, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Gruen, John, 1959-1984, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Guggenheim, Peggy, 1971 July 19 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Hale, Sheila; Hale, John, 1970-1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Haught, Enid A., 1980 February 19 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Haye, Claire, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Hempstead, Eleanor, n.y. January 26 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Hirzel, Pauline Mills, 1958-1982 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Hughes, Liam, 1982 June 26 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Hume, Ruth; Hume, Paul, 1962, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - [Kellmen?], Chester, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Kennedy, Robert F., 1965 February 2 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Kimball, Florence Page, 1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Kirstein, Lincoln, 1980, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Kissinger, Nancy, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Koegler, Horst, 1956 August 7 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Lambiotte, Auguste; Lambiotte, Rose, 1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Lassalle, Nancy, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Leach, Richard P., 1962 October 2 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Le Brocquy, Louis, 1983 October 24 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Legendre, Michel, 1968 May 15 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Lepercq, Dave, 1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - McCall Publishing Company, 1970 June 26 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - MacLeish, Ada; MacLeish, Archibald, 1965 January 11 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Magriel, Paul, 1980, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Malanovitzky, Paul; Malanovitzky, Barbara, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Mann, Claire, n.y. March 12 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Marandel, J. P., 1980 February 10 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Mason, Marsha, 1984 May 7 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Mathews, Mary, 1980 January 17 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Matisse, Pierre; Matisse, [Gaetana], 1981 April 30 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Maynard, Mrs. Walter, 1979 October 24 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - [Merrill?], James, 1956-1982 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Milhaud, Madeleine, 1981 September 7 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Moore, John, 1980 October 7 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Murdock, William Gordon; Peschka, Francis J., 1958-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 86)
    Includes watercolor and printed material
  - Osborn, Robert, 1962 October 1 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Paley, William S., 1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Paulvé, Dominique, 1980 February 10 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Pecci Blunt, Anna Laetitia, 1964 May 31 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Pezzoni, Enrique, 1971-1980 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Porter, Fairfield, 1956 August 4 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Radziwill, Lee, 1983-1984, undated (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Rehr, Helen, 1959, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Robbins, Jerome, 1973-1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Roberts, Isabel, 1959-1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Rockefeller, Mary C., n.y. November 9 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - [Rothschild?], Liliane de, 1982-1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Rubin de Cervin, Marie-Teresa, 1972-1983 (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Satie, Joseph Lafosse, 1980 October 15 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Schimmel, Herbert, undated (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Schippers, Thomas, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Schuman, William, 1962 October 11 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Seaver, Jeannette S. M., n.y. September 30 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Sellerio, Enzo, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Shaw, R., 1971 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Souzay, Gérard, 1964 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Spender, Stephen, 1971 July 16 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Steinberg, William, 1970 January 19 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Stravinsky, Soulima, n.y. February 5 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - Strickland, P. Roy, 1980 September 29 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - Talbott, Harold, 1965-1984, undated (Box 3, Folder 112-126)
  - Tanning, Dorothea, 1963-1983, undated (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - Thomson, Virgil, 1980 March 29 (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Torricini, Angelo, 1966-1983, undated (Box 4, Folder 129-131)
  - Torricini, Claude, 1956-1980, undated (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Tully, Alice, 1973 March (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - Vanderbilt, Jean; Vanderbilt, Alfred, 1966-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Vreeland, Diana, 1980, undated (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - White, Robert, 1971 June 11 (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Wilson, Edmund, 1965 January 14 (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - Worth, Irene, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 138)
  - First name only, 1956-1984, undated (Box 4, Folder 139-141)
  - Others and unidentified, 1956-1983, undated (Box 4, Folder 142)
  - Fan mail, 1980-1983, undated (Box 4, Folder 143-145)
  - Empty envelopes, 1962, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 146)
- Other Papers, 1970-1991; Series II; 0.21; (1 box) + 1 broadside folder
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series II. Other Papers contains manuscript material, photographs, printed ephemera, and material relating to the pianists' book on Sarah Bernhardt.
  - Last will and testament of Arthur Gold, undated (Box 5, Folder 147)
  - Manuscript material, undated (Box 5, Folder 148)
  - Misia lecture, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 149)
  - Photographs, 1970-1981, undated (Box 5, Folder 150)
  - Printed ephemera, 1973-1983, undated (Box 5, Folder 151)
  - Sarah Bernhardt material, 1991, undated (Box 5, Folder 152)
  - Sarah Bernhardt material, undated (Box 6 (Broadside), Folder 153)